<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE component SYSTEM "componentinfo.dtd">
<!-- component.xml.  Generated from component.xml.in by configure. -->

<component id="hds" support="S">
  <version>6.2</version>
  <path>libraries/hds</path>
  <description>Hierarchical Data System</description>
  <abstract>
    <p>HDS is a file-based hierarchical data system designed for the
      storage of a wide variety of information. It is particularly
      suited to the storage of large multi-dimensional arrays (with
      their ancillary data) where efficient access is needed.</p>
    <p>HDS organises data into hierarchies, broadly similar to the
      directory structure of a hierarchical filing system, but
      contained within a single HDS container file.  The
      structures stored in these files are self-describing and
      flexible; HDS supports modification and extension of structures
      previously created, as well as deletion, copying, renaming, etc..</p>
    <p>All information stored in HDS files is portable between the
      machines on which HDS is implemented. Thus, there are no format
      conversion problems when moving between machines.</p>
    <p>The routines in this package may be used to perform operations
      on any HDS data. In addition, HDS forms a toolkit for the
      construction of higher level (more specialised) data structures
      and the software which accesses them.  HDS routines are
      therefore invoked indirectly by many other items of Starlink
      software.</p>
  </abstract>
  <dependencies >
    <build>sae</build><build>chr</build><build>cnf</build><build>ems</build><build>starmem</build><build>one</build><build>hds-v4</build><build>hds-v5</build><link>chr</link><link>cnf</link><link>ems</link><link>starmem</link><link>one</link><link>hds-v4</link><link>hds-v5</link><test>chr</test><test>cnf</test><test>ems</test><test>prm</test><test>starmem</test><test>one</test><test>hds-v4</test><test>hds-v5</test><sourceset>star2html</sourceset><sourceset>messgen</sourceset>
  </dependencies>
  <developers>
    <person>
      <name>R. F. Warren-Smith</name>
    </person>
    <person>
      <name>M. D. Lawden</name>
    </person>
    <person>
      <name>Brian McIlwrath</name>
      <uname>bkm</uname>
      <email>B.K.McIlwrath@rl.ac.uk</email>
      <role>owner</role>
    </person>
  </developers>
  <documentation> sun92</documentation>
  <bugreports>starlink@jiscmail.ac.uk</bugreports>
  <!-- <notes><p></p></notes> -->
</component>
