<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE component SYSTEM "componentinfo.dtd">
<!-- component.xml.  Generated from component.xml.in by configure. -->

<component id="sun90">
  <version>9</version>
  <path>docs/sun/090</path>
  <description>SNX --- Starlink Extensions to the NCAR Graphics Utilities</description>
  <abstract><p>
     The NCAR graphics suite (SUN/88) consists of a set of subprograms
     which can be used to produce complete graphs in a variety of
     formats.  The package has been in wide use for some years; the
     latest version employs the ISO standard GKS interfaces for its
     low-level plotting, giving it access to all Starlink graphics
     devices, present and future.

     The NCAR routines themselves are thoroughly documented, and just
     a few simple calls will produce graphs of excellent appearance.
     The package also provides a high level of flexibility, with
     dozens of different details of the plot independently
     controllable to give exactly the result required.  However,
     beginners may be daunted by the mass of features offered, and
     unless they take the extreme step of reading the manual may give
     up before they realise what the package can do for them.  This
     document describes minor extensions which provide more convenient
     access to certain features without sacrificing flexibility.

     The AUTOGRAPH part of the NCAR suite, used in conjunction with
     the Starlink NCAR extensions and the Starlink low level plotting
     package SGS (SUN/85), offers an alternative high level system to
     PGPLOT (SUN/15) for producing graphs of one variable plotted
     against another. All of the Starlink extensions provided within
     SNX enhance the power of the facilities provided by AUTOGRAPH and
     make it more accessible to the beginner.
  </p></abstract>  
  <dependencies >
    <sourceset>star2html</sourceset>
  </dependencies>
  <developers>
    <person>
      <name>P C T Rees</name>
      <name>M J Bly</name>
      <name>P T Wallace</name>
    </person>
  </developers>
  <documentation> sun90</documentation>
  <bugreports>ussc@star.rl.ac.uk</bugreports>
  <copyright>
    <year>1987,1988,1989,1990,1991,1992,1993,1994,1995</year>
    <name>PPARC</name>
  </copyright>
</component>
