<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE sun PUBLIC
              "-//Starlink//DTD Starlink SUN 0.7 (XML)//EN"
              "dtd/ssn-xml-0.7.dtd">
<!-- $Revision$ -->

<sun>
<docinfo>
<title>Building Starlink Software</title>
<authorlist>
<author webpage="http://www.astro.gla.ac.uk/users/norman/"
  affiliation="Starlink/University of Glasgow" role="author" id="ng"
  >Norman Gray</author>
<author affiliation="Starlink, Rutherford Appleton Laboratory" id="ser"
  >Steve Rankin</author>
<author affiliation="Starlink/University of Durham" id="pwd"
  >Peter Draper</author>
</authorlist>
<docnumber>248</docnumber>
<history>
<version number="1" date="02-Apr-2007" author="pwd">
<px>Draft release: $Revision$</px>
</version>
</history>
</docinfo>

<docbody>
<abstract>

<px><code>This document is now out of date as the Starlink project has been closed.
See <url>http://www.starlink.ac.uk</url>. Releases are currently (April 2007) 
made by the 
<webref url="http://www.jach.hawaii.edu/software/starlink/">JAC</webref>.  
Build instructions are now only updated in the main README file, which you can
find in a source distribution (the instructions in this document remain
relevant for downloading that), or at:
<url>http://cvsweb.starlink.ac.uk/cvsweb.cgi/README</url>.  
Platform specific instructions are also now found in the README only, the ones
in this document are for historic purposes only. </code>
</px>

<px>
Old introduction beings...
</px>

<px>This document contains instructions on how to build the Starlink `classic'
software from source and a comparison with the old 'mk-based' build system.
This document is deliberately terse, since we have invested effort in making
the processes involved as easy as possible.
</px>

<px><tabular>
<tgroup cols="1">
  <tbody>
  <row><entry>$Revision$</entry></row>
  <row><entry>$Date$</entry></row>
  </tbody>
</tgroup>
</tabular>
</px>
</abstract>



<sect id="intro" export="export">
<subhead>
<title>Building and installing Starlink software: generic instructions</title>
</subhead>

<p>Starlink distributes its software products in a variety of ways.</p>

<p>The Project makes periodic binary releases.  These are made every
six months in principle, though the intervals are usually somewhat
longer in fact.  The set of platforms Starlink targets is not fixed, but in the
latest release the list was Linux RHEL3, RH9 and Debian3.0, and Sparc
8/9, with a beta release for Mac OS X.  For fuller details, see the
`Software' link on the <webref url="http://www.starlink.ac.uk"
>Starlink home page</webref>.</p>

<p>All the software in such a release is also available as source
tarballs, and some components of the software set make interim source
releases, also as source tarballs.  This document is about how to
build, and once built how to link against, these distributed source
tarballs.  It is a short document, since it is our intention that
building and installing our software should be as simple as
<verbatim>
% ./configure; make; make install
</verbatim>
exactly as for the majority of open-source software available now.
Except where some technicality prevents it, all the Starlink libraries
are installed as both static and shared libraries, and there should be
no surprises in linking agsinst them.  The only difference from the
standard behaviour is that the default installation prefix for our
software is in either <code>/star</code> or <code>/stardev</code> (the
latter for interim releases or beta software), rather than
<code>/usr/local</code>.  You can confirm this with <kbd>./configure
--help</kbd>.
</p>

<p>The software should build without problems, as we have invested
considerable effort in making it portable across platforms and
compilers.  As with any other very large software system, however, we
are aware of some wrinkles, and these are discussed in the
platform-specific notes in <ref id="platform"/> below.  If you find
any other problems, or have other comments on the build system, please
do get in touch with the Project, through the general contact address
<webref url="mailto:starlink@jiscmail.ac.uk"
><code>starlink@jiscmail.ac.uk</code></webref>.</p>

<p>You may be used to Starlink's earlier build system, based on
<code>./mk</code> scripts.  This is now obsolete, and a migration path
is outlined in <ref id="mk-migration"/> below.</p>

<p>This document is concerned only with the Starlink `classic'
applications, and does not cover the newer Java applications.  See
<url>http://www.starlink.ac.uk/java/java.htm</url> for details about these.</p>

<subsect id="starcvs" export="export">
<subhead>
<title>The Starlink CVS repository</title>
</subhead>

<p>All of Starlink's source code is kept in a CVS repository, which is
publicly available (a CVS repository is a central library of source
code, maintained in such a way that multiple individuals can have
convenient access to it it; for further details see
<url>http://www.astro.gla.ac.uk/users/norman/note/2003/cvsprimer/</url>
for example).</p>

<p>The Starlink build system consists of
<ul>
<li>
<p>the Starlink CVS repository;</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>build tools, consisting of modified versions of the GNU
autotools <code>autoconf</code> <code>automake</code>
and <code>libtool</code>;</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>configuration and bootstrap code, consisting of the
<code>starconf</code> system and the scripts at the top
level of the Starlink source tree.</p>
</li>

</ul>
</p>

<p>The repository is on the machine <code>cvs.starlink.ac.uk</code>.  See
<url>http://www.starlink.ac.uk/Download/getcvs.html</url> for details
of checking out the software and building the system.</p>

<p>The <code>getcvs.html</code> web page above says that, after
checking the source tree out of CVS, you should read the
<code>README</code> at the top of the tree.  There are
platform-specific notes about this in <ref id="platform"/> below.</p>

<p>The build system as a whole is described in considerable detail in
<docxref doc="SSN/78">SSN/78</docxref>.  This is a large document, but
you probably don't have to read it, if what you want to do with the
Starlink applications and libraries is to build them from distributed
source tarballs, use the applications, and link against the libraries
from your own programs.  You will only need to read SSN/78 if you wish
to
<ol>
<li>
<p>build from the up-to-the-minute versions in the CVS repository
(though even in that case, you are probably better with the
up-to-the-day versions available in the nightly build tarballs at
<url>http://dev.starlink.ac.uk/build/</url>);</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>work on the CVS sources themselves, since you are welcome to play
with the versions of the sources available as an anonymous CVS
checkout; or</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>you wish to add further components to the Starlink CVS repository,
though in this case you should probably talk to the Project first, to
coordinate your efforts with others.</p>
</li>
</ol>
</p>
</subsect>

</sect>

<sect id="platform" export="export">
<subhead>
<title>Platform-specific notes</title>
</subhead>

<p>To build the software set, you should follow the
<code>README</code> at the top level of the checked-out tree.  You can
examine the current version of this file, and its history, at
<url>http://cvsweb.starlink.ac.uk/cvsweb.cgi/README</url>.</p>

<p>In particular, note that you will have to have &latex; installed
on your machine, or the build will fail when building documentation,
at an irritatingly late stage of the process.  This and other remarks
are rehearsed in the <code>README</code>, mentioned above.</p>

<p><code>April 2007: the notes below are known to be out of date
please refer to the README file for newer instructions on what is known
about platform specifics.</code>
</p>

<p>The notes below are of the specific type which tends to become either wrong
or redundant rather promptly.  If they have become wrong by the time
you read this, please try to get in touch with the project (not
trivial, since we have been shut down even as I write) to tell the sorry
maintainer of this document how it should be amended or clarified.
Ideally, there will be a bugzilla server somewhere near
<url>http://dev.starlink.ac.uk/</url>.</p>

<subsect id="platform-osx" export="export">
<subhead>
<title>Building on OS X</title>
</subhead>

<p>You need a Fortran compiler: although the system compiler on OS X
is GCC, Apple don't include g77 in their distribution.</p>

<p>You can get a g77 package from either <webref
url="http://darwinports.opendarwin.org/" >DarwinPorts</webref> or
<webref url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/" >Fink</webref>.  Darwinports
is (in Norman's experience) rather more <webref
url="http://darwinports.opendarwin.org/getdp/" >fiddly to
set up</webref> than Fink, but it is possibly to be preferred, since it has a
certain amount of Apple support and contributions from Apple
employees; it appears to be more deliberately aligned with the GCC
version in the OS X distribution; and there are suggestions that Apple
may at some point `bless' it, and make it more easily integrated with
a standard OS X setup.  Since the two projects are now reportedly
sharing code, the distinction between them should increasingly become
one of style rather than of quantity.</p>

<p>Once you've installed one of the g77 packages, and put the appropriate binary directory in your PATH, you should be ready to go.</p>

<p>If you want to build and install the documentation then you should
install TeX on Mac OS X (get the <code>gwTeX</code> distribution
(good) from <url>http://www.rna.nl/tex.html</url>; there are other
notes about TeX on OS X at
<url>http://www.esm.psu.edu/mac-tex/</url>). Otherwise use:
<verbatim>
% ./configure -C --disable-shared --without-stardocs
</verbatim>
You might also have to install ghostscript from Darwinports or Fink.</p>

<p>You should also install the Apple X11 distribution, including the
X11-SDK: this should be included on your Mac OS X distribution media,
but depending on that distribution's version may or may not installed
by default.  The OS X development tools (based on <code>gcc</code>)
may, again, be on your distribution media, but if they are not may be
found on an inadequately stable URL somewhere near
<url>http://developer.apple.com/macosx/</url>.  Do not use the
Darwinports or Fink X11.</p>

</subsect>

<subsect id="platform-tru64" export="export">
<subhead>
<title>Building on Tru64</title>
</subhead>

<p>The configure script will choose a Fortran 95 compiler before it
settles for a Fortran 77 one. Some of the code requires a Fortran 77
compiler (at least at present, possibly indefinitely), and so if you
have more than one Fortran compiler installed, you'll have to force
the build system with a command like:
<verbatim>
% ./configure FC=f77 [other arguments]
</verbatim>
where the Tru64 Fortran 77 compiler is called <code>f77</code>.  You
can give the path to the compiler also, if the f77 you want isn't the
first one in your <code>PATH</code>.  Since this sort of robustness is
the sort of thing we'll continue to work on, don't do this until you
have empirically determined that it won't work otherwise.</p>

<p>The Tru64 C and C++ compilers should work fine: if you have more
than one compiler installed, you can force them with the configure
arguments <code>CC=cc</code> and <code>CXX=cxx</code>; but this
shouldn't be necessary.</p>

</subsect>


<subsect id="platform-solaris" export="export">
<subhead>
<title>Building on Solaris</title>
</subhead>

<p>The configure script will choose a Fortran 95 compiler before it
settles for a Fortran 77 one. Some of the code requires a Fortran 77
compiler, which means that, if you have more than one Fortran compiler
installed, you'll have to force the build system with a command like:
<verbatim>
% ./configure FC=f77 F77=f77 FPPFLAGS='-P -fixed' [other arguments]
</verbatim>
where the Solaris Fortran 77 compiler is called <code>f77</code>. You
can give the path to the compiler also, if the f77 you want isn't the
first one in your <code>PATH</code>.  Since this sort of robustness is
the sort of thing we'll continue to work on, don't do this until you
have empirically determined that it won't work otherwise.</p>

<p>This dependence on a Fortran 77 compiler is true at present, and
may be the case indefinitely; at least part of the problem is the
current repository version of libtool,
which appears not to understand <code>f95</code> on Solaris, so this
problem might 
go away with a libtool update.  As libtool doesn't understand the
<code>FC</code> flag, the <code>F77</code> variable has to be set to
match the <code>FC</code> one.</p>

<p>The Solaris C and C++ compilers should work fine: if you have more
than one compiler installed, you can force the choice with the
configure arguments <code>CC=cc</code> and <code>CXX=CC</code>, but
this shouldn't be necessary. The system works with gcc and g++ on
Solaris, too, and these compilers can be selected using the same
mechanism.</p>

</subsect>

<subsect id="platform-cygwin" export="export">
<subhead>
<title>Building on Cygwin</title>
</subhead>

<p>The configure script fails to identify how to preprocess Fortran,
so it necessary to set environment variables with a command like:
<verbatim>
% ./configure FPP=g77 FPPFLAGS='-E' [other arguments]
</verbatim>
</p>

</subsect>

<subsect id="platform-x86" export="export">
<subhead>
<title>Building on x86</title>
</subhead>

<p>There are no known problems building on x86 boxes.</p>

<p>Whoopee, and all that.</p>
</subsect>

<subsect id="platform-x86-64" export="export">
<subhead>
<title>Building on 64-bit x86</title>
</subhead>

<p>The only known problem on x86_64 appears to be a
distribution-specific one. On RHEL, the the various 1.x versions of
the <code>tetex</code> package install the <code>kpathsea</code>
library as a static library alone, and not a shared one. This produces
an error message when compiling the <code>dvi2bitmap</code> component,
resembling:
<verbatim>
ld: ./libkpathsea.a(tex-file.o): relocation R_X86_64_32 can not be used when making a shared object; recompile with -fPIC
./libkpathsea.a: could not read symbols: Bad value
</verbatim>
</p>

<p>To address this, you can either configure <code>dvi2bitmap</code>
using <code>--without-kpathsea</code> at some loss in functionality,
or else recompile the kpathsea library yourself. The sources are
available at <webref url="http://www.tug.org/ftp/tex/web2c.tar.gz"
>TUG</webref> -- you need to rebuild only the kpathsea part of this
distribution: to do that:
<ol>
<li><p>Unpack the distribution, and go to the <code>web2c-x.x.x</code>
directory.</p></li>

<li><p>Configure using <code>./configure --enable-shared --datadir=XXX
--prefix=PREFIX</code>, where <code>XXX</code> is the location
of teTeX on your local machine (probably <code>/usr/share</code> on
RHEL) and <code>PREFIX</code> is where you would like the newly-built
library to be installed.</p></li>

<li><p>cd to the kpathsea directory, and delete the lines in the
Makefile that refer to (unwritable) <code>$(web2cdir)</code>.</p></li>

<li><p><code>make; make install</code> to install in
<code>PREFIX</code>.</p></li>

</ol>
The installation directory <code>PREFIX</code> will have to be in your
<code>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</code> when you re-configure
<code>dvi2bitmap</code>.  As usual, don't go to all this trouble until
you've determined that it won't work otherwise.</p>

</subsect>
</sect>

<sect id="mk-migration" export="export">
<subhead>
<title>Migration from a ./mk based build system</title>
</subhead>

<p>The Starlink code set is now built using the standard (or at least,
conventional) autoconf system, so that you configure the system before
building using the command <code>./configure</code>. See the sections above
for whatever platform-specific discussion remains necessary.</p>

<p>The Plan is that you need the standard magic
<verbatim>
./configure; make; make install
</verbatim>
to build and install any of the distributed components.</p>

<p>This is rather different from the old Starlink system, which used a
<code>mk</code> script, which set up a number of environment variables to
platform-specific values and then invoked make on your behalf. The
<code>mk</code> script consisted of a switch which set appropriate
values for each of the platforms which the Project supported (plus
sometimes a few other contributed ones). The configure-based system
should be more portable, and work on a broader range of platforms
without such platform-specific customisation.</p>

<p>If you have previously built software using the
<code>mk</code>-based system, you will see little difference in the
new system, beyond the difference in procedure described above.</p>

<p>If, on the other hand, you have previously <em>developed</em> using the
<code>mk</code>-based system, there will be a few more changes:
<ol>
<li><p><code>mk</code> scripts will no longer work.</p></li>

<li><p>The <code>INSTALL</code> and <code>SYSTEM</code> environment
variables have disappeared.</p></li>

<li><p>The <code>xxx_dev</code> scripts have disappeared.</p></li>

<li><p>The system now uses shared libraries extensively, and you might
have to indicate where these are.</p></li> 
</ol>
</p>

<p>If you are simply linking against Starlink libraries, you probably
don't have to care about any of this, and the only difference is that
you now have shared libraries and centrally located include files to
make your job easier.  Most of the libraries in the distribution are
built using <code>libtool</code>, and the libtool <code>.la</code>
`library files' are installed.</p>

<p>If you are planning to work on applications in the CVS repository,
you should probably take a look at <docxref
doc="SSN/78">SSN/78</docxref>, and might want to introduce yourself on
the Starlink developers mailing list, at
<url>http://www.jiscmail.ac.uk/lists/stardev.html</url>.</p>

<subsect id="mk-mk" export="export">
<subhead>
<title>mk scripts</title>
</subhead>

<p>mk scripts are now obsolete.  If you have made or modified a
<code>mk</code> script of your own, you will certainly need to rework
things to fit in with the new system. SSN/78 describes the new build
system in detail, along with introductions to the autotools and
pointers to fuller documentation.  The new system is an improvement --
trust me.</p>
</subsect>

<subsect id="mk-install" export="export">
<subhead>
<title>The INSTALL and SYSTEM variables</title>
</subhead>

<p>The <code>INSTALL</code> and <code>SYSTEM</code> variables have
disappeared.</p>

<p>The <code>SYSTEM</code> variable used to specify the system on
which the software was being built, and the <code>mk</code> script
switched on this value to make its settings, making the assumption
that the platform reliably implied the compilers being used. This is
now redundant, since the autoconf-based system makes its decision, not
on the basis of what platform it discovers it is running on, but on
the basis of the tools and capabilities it dynamically discovers. This
variable is now simply ignored.</p>

<p>The <code>INSTALL</code> variable used to specify the installation
location; this role is now performed by the <code>--prefix...=</code>
option to the <code>./configure</code> script.  There is a major clash
of conventions here: the generated <code>./configure</code> script
will look at the <code>INSTALL</code> variable and, if it is set,
expect it to name a program to use instead of the standard
<code>/usr/bin/install</code> program, to install the software after
building.  You should almost certainly <em>not</em> have this variable
defined, and if it is defined by accident, to anything other than an
installation program, the buildsystem will almost certainly fail very
messily.</p>

<p>See the top-level <code>README</code> file for further details about
environment variables which affect the build.</p>
</subsect>

<subsect id="mk-dev" export="export">
<subhead>
<title>The xxx_dev scripts, and include files</title>
</subhead>

<p>The <code>xxx_dev</code> scripts and include files have changed.</p>

<p>In the <code>mk</code> system, the <code>xxx_dev</code> scripts had
to be used to make soft links to the (Fortran) include files necessary
for working with a library.  In the new system, all such include files
are installed in a standard place, such as /star/include.  All the
Fortran compilers that we are aware of have a <code>-I</code> option
to indicate where such include files are to be found.</p>

<p>Note that the names of the Fortran include files are now
consistently upper-case.</p>

</subsect>

<subsect id="mk-shared" export="export">
<subhead>
<title>Shared libraries: some observations</title>
</subhead>

<p>With only one or two exceptions, all the Starlink libraries are
built and installed as shared libraries, as well as static ones.  This
is as normal, and if you refer to a library in the usual way, with a
<code>-l</code> option, your system will do The Right Thing.  On those
few occasions where there are library complications (AST, for example,
can be linked in a surprising variety of ways), the details will be
described in the package documentation.</p>

<p>The build system uses <webref
url="http://directory.fsf.org/libtool.html" >libtool</webref>
extensively, and it installs its `libtool library files',
<code>wibble.la</code>, in the library directory alongside the more
usual static <code>.a</code> and dynamic <code>.so</code> files (as
appropriate for your platform).  If you also use libtool, you might
usefully link against these <code>.la</code> files yourself.</p>

<p>Given the choice, most linkers will prefer to link against a shared
library, but if the difference matters to you, you will probably
already know how to make your linker do what you want.  Recall that on many
Unixes, the environment variable <code>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</code>
specifies a list of directories which are searched for shared
libraries, in addition to a set of system defaults; the analogue on
Mac OS X is <code>DYLD_LIBRARY_PATH</code>.</p>

<p>Systems tend to differ markedly in the details of their linker
behaviour.  See your system's <code>ld</code> man page for more
details than a sane mind can comfortably encompass.</p>

</subsect>
</sect>

</docbody>

</sun>

<!-- Local Variables: -->
<!-- sgml-indent-data: nil -->
<!-- sgml-indent-step: 0 -->
<!-- End: -->
