<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE defectslist SYSTEM "defects.dtd">

<defectslist>

<title>SGML project issues list</title>

<version>$Revision$</version>
<date>$Date$</date>

<p>This list contains the current defects list for
the Starlink General and Programcode DTDs.  As well as specific
deficiencies, these `defects' include items which are merely
suggestions or TODOs</p>

<p>If it's not in here, I don't plan to do anything about it (which
probably means I've forgotten about it, and you should remind
me).</p>

<p>These are in no particular order, and some have a higher priority
than others.</p>

<!-- DO NOT CHANGE THE ORDER OF ELEMENTS IN THIS FILE.
     They're numbered when they're formatted, and it'd be nice to keep
     those numbers correct.
     -->

<defectgroup>
<title>General DTD</title>

<defect status="closed" originator="Mark">
<title>Implement a FOREIGN element</title>
<p>Support such things as &lt;foreign&gt;et. al.&lt;/foreign&gt;.
Dead easy to do.</p>
<resolution status="fixed" author="Norman" date="00-Mar-2000">
<p>Done.</p>
</resolution>
</defect>

<defect status="closed" originator="Rodney">
<title>Non-sentence-ending periods</title>
<p>Include an abbrev element?  nbsp entity?</p>
<resolution status="fixed" author="Norman" date="21-Mar-2000"
	note="entities-latex.ent, rev 1.9, and entities-html.ent, rev 1.9">
<p>Added a &amp;dot; entity to indicate a non-sentence-ending period.</p>
</resolution>
</defect>

<defect status="open" originator="DSB">
<title>LaTeX as alt format </title>
<p>Some documents could use a specialised layout for some section
headings.  Possibly include a LaTeX-formatted element, which
could be used as an alternative, but legitimately ignored.</p>
<p>I'm open to concrete suggestions for the syntax of this -- is this
a real priority?</p>
</defect>

<defect status="closed" originator="ACD">
<title>Hours and degrees elements</title>
<p>Clive even supplied SGML and LaTeX to support this!  Just a
matter of slotting them in when I'm next fiddling with that DTD.
</p>
<resolution status="fixed" author="Norman" date="00-Apr-2000">
<p>Incorporated Clive's fixes.</p>
</resolution>
</defect>

<defect status="open" originator="Norman/Mark">
<title>Admonition</title>
<p>At same level as BLOCKQUOTE, with a couple of `class'
attributes.  Should one of these classes be `epigraph'...?
</p>
</defect>

<defect status="open" originator="prog meeting">
<title>Bibliography within source document</title>
<p>Some folk don't (want to) use BibTeX, so it may be worth
supporting bib elements within the document if that doesn't
make things too complicated (could I simply mimic BibTeX?).
</p>
</defect>

<defect status="open" date="15-Sep-1999" originator="Mark">
<title>Cross-references to CODECOLLECTIONs</title>
<p>Mark pointed out that this is OK from within the document
which references them, but it's not necessarily easy from
within another document.  This is potentially rather knotty, I
think, but it'll be quite interesting to solve.</p>
<p>Also (Mark):
I'm not sure this is closed - you need to be able to reference, e.g.,
the KAPPA DISPLAY documentation from documents other than SUN/95.  
I think it is undesirable that the authors of other documents should
need to know the name and location of the SGML document which
constitutes the list of KAPPA routines.  Hence inserting the KAPPA 
codecollection element which is required for coderef elements to work 
is problematic in documents other than SUN/95.</p>
<p>Bother -- of course.  I'll think further on this.</p>

<resolution status="deferred" author="Norman" date="10-May-2000"
note="starlink-0.7.dtd, rev 1.2">
<p>This is fixed in the simple case where a document wants to
reference routines in its own CODECOLLECTION.  Alongside the REF and
DOCXREF elements is now a CODEREF 
element, which refers to IDs within programcode documents by
indirection via the CODECOLLECTION element which references the
programcode.</p>
<p>The `codexref' problem is still open.</p>
</resolution>
</defect>

<defect status="closed" originator="Mark" date="04-Apr-2000"
	note="Commentary on m element in starlink-0.7">
<title>Maths in help files.</title>
<p>Quoth Mark:</p>
<p>Have we any ideas what to do with math content for help downconverters
(or any other downconverters to non-graphical output)?
A latex -> eqn (eqn is a roff preprocessor) converter would be a good start, 
though it obviously couldn't cope with everything; however a quick 
search doesn't reveal that any such thing exists.  </p>

<p>As things stand the only robust alternative I can see is spitting out the
latex content, but this is not very friendly to help file readers.</p>

<p>Maybe we need a mechanism which can contain an alternative 
ascii-art representation of the latex-notation content.  
This probably needs to be an optional, verbatim-like, element rather 
than an attribute since it may need line breaks to make sense.
In practice, as far as I can see, this is only going to
be a problem for programcode not main document text, since only 
programcode gets converted to an ascii-like format (unless we envisage
people reading SUNs with lynx??).  But if we make a modification,
it's probably best to programcode and main DTDs alike.</p>
<resolution status="fixed" author="Mark" date="5-Jun-2000">
<p>Quoth Mark, again:</p>
<p>I think this can be considered closed, since the
<code>&lt;span&gt;</code> element is the 
proper way of dealing with this sort of thing.  That's not completely
resolved, but further discussion should be under the span heading,
not here.</p>
</resolution>
</defect>

<defect status="closed" originator="Norman">
<title>Document cross-references</title>
<p>The DTD has been converted to XML, in the sense that it's possible
to write a limited document which conforms to a XMLised version of the 
general DTD.  However, DOCXREF elements are one of the areas where
this is deficient.  This will require some careful thought, since
DOCXREF at present relies on subdocument entities, which don't exist
in XML.  It shouldn't be too hard to produce a replacement, since such 
entities can be converted into NDATA entities with an SGML or XML notation.</p>
<resolution status="fixed" author="Norman" date="21-aug-2003">
<p>This was in fact easy.  dsssl/sl/{html,latex}/sllinks.dsl modified</p>
</resolution>
</defect>

<defect status="open" originator="Norman">
<title>Unicode entities in conversion to LaTeX</title>
<p>The entity sets which are used when parsing XML are specified in
terms of Unicode character points.  The HTML output appears not to
cause problems, but it does causes problems for 
LaTeX, which reacts badly when it encounters \char65440 or the like.
This problem is, I'm positive, superable in LaTeX, but messy.  This
should probably be deferred until after the rewrite of the processing
system.  At present, it's been `fixed' by defining the `unicode'
entities as ordinary characters.</p>
</defect>

</defectgroup>

<defectgroup>
<title>Programcode DTD</title>

<defect status="closed" originator="prog meeting">
<title>Allow ampersand connector in codeprologue</title>
<p>The order of the element children of routineprologue should be
arbitrary.  Also, use the SST elements.</p>
<resolution status="fixed" author="Norman" date="19-Sep-1999">
<p>Supported in DCs as of 19 Sept -- it just doesn't look very nice.
This won't work in XML, but that's OK since these'll usually be SGML
sources.</p>
</resolution>
</defect>

<defect status="open" originator="Mark">
<title>Shortrefs in programcode DTD</title>
<p>Shortrefs to make lists in prologues tidier.  Nice, but I'm
always nervous of having too much cleverness in this area,
because the more shortrefs there are, the easier it is to type
one by accident, and so provoke a completely unintelligible
error message.  I don't plan to do anything with this before
we've discussed it at greater length.
</p>
</defect>

<defect status="closed" originator="Mark" date="14-Sep-1999">
<title>AUTHORREF element</title>
<p>`The AUTHORLIST element is a nasty example of SGML forcing one
to write something which one otherwise wouldn't want to'.
This is probably true, but there are no ideal alternatives, I
don't think.
</p>
<resolution status="fixed" author="Norman" date="17-May-2000"
	note="programcode-0.7.dtd, rev 1.4">
<p>After some discussion, the AUTHORREF element was removed, and the
`id' attribute on the AUTHOR element demoted to CDATA, with the
extra-syntactic constraint that the same CDATA string throughout a
document (or indeed the whole documentation set!) would be taken
to refer to the same author.  This makes the
association between authors less robust, but much more convenient.</p>
</resolution>
</defect>

<defect status="closed" originator="Mark" date="14-Sep-1999">
<title>DL/DD/DT/BLOCKQUOTE/VERBATIM/M in prologues </title>
<p>Easy, I think.</p>
<resolution status="fixed" author="Norman" date="19-Sep-2000">
<p>Implemented by restructuring the General and Programcode
DTDs so that they both include a common set of para-level
elements.  No additional DC support needed, since the DC
support for the General DTD takes care of this.  Just needs
documented quickly.</p>
</resolution>
</defect>

<defect status="closed" originator="Mark/Norman" date="07-Apr-2000">
<title>Programcode DTD variant for scripts</title>
<p>This should involve nothing more
sophisticated than adding #+, # and #- to the shortref list in the
declaration.</p>
<resolution status="deferred" author="Norman" date="29-May-2000">
<p>Norman and Mark have been discussing this.  Norman has gone off the
idea somewhat, because he's suspicious of the potential for chaos
represented by shortrefs in general.  Mark is enthusiastic, because it
obviates the need for any sed magic when building documentation.  We
left it in the air somewhat: a scriptcode DTD is present in the 0.7
release, with Norman claiming a couple of problems with it.  If either
of us wants to tidy it up at all, we can.</p>
</resolution>
</defect>

<defect status="open" originator="Mark" date="07-Apr-2000"
	note="Commentary on programcode-0.7+parameter">
<title>Array sizes in parameter elements</title>
<p>Quoth Mark:</p>
<p>There are various possibilities to accommodate this:
   1)  A 'shape' attribute (CDATA) on the &lt;type> or &lt;parameter> elements
   2)  A &lt;shape> optional element (PCDATA) in the content of &lt;type>
          or &lt;parameter>
   3)  Just write the size as part of the PCDATA content of &lt;type></p>
<p>I suggest (3), so one would have
<verbatim>
   *  &lt;parameter given>
   *     ORIGIN = _INTEGER( 3 )
</verbatim></p>
</defect>

</defectgroup>

<defectgroup>
<title>Down-converters</title>

<defect status="open" originator="Mark">
<title>LaTeX: Nested CODE elements</title>
<p>CODE elements within other elements like STRONG don't always
come out in tt-type.</p>
</defect>

<defect status="open" originator="Mark">
<title>LaTeX: Process picture environments with maths in DC</title>
<p>Should be fairly easy.  Can I do metapost at the same time?</p>
</defect>

<defect status="open" originator="Norman/Mark">
<title>SDATA entities</title>
<p>...are a mess.  Perhaps this should wait until I build and
incorporate OpenJade 1.3, which has map-sdata-entity support,
when I can do it properly.</p>
</defect>

<defect status="open" originator="Norman">
<title>LaTeX: DT element</title>
<p>Tweak the generated LaTeX so that {description} \item s are
cleverer about spacing.</p>
</defect>

<defect status="open" originator="Mark" date="9-Sep-1999">
<title>LaTeX: REF/maths in DT in LaTeX doesn't insert text</title>
<p>Haven't investigated</p>
</defect>

<defect status="open" originator="Mark">
<title>LaTeX: pages are smaller than standard, and positioned differently</title>
<p>Should need only the most minor tweaking.</p>
</defect>

<defect status="open" originator="Mark">
<title>KBD in VERBATIM doesn't work</title>
<p>Haven't investigated</p>
</defect>

<defect status="closed" originator="Rodney, Mark">
<title>Script-driven downconversion</title>
<p>At present, this is little more than an alias for make, and so
could probably be made more sophisticated without breaking
anything....</p>
<resolution status="fixed" author="Norman" date="00-Jan-2000">
<p>Replaced by sgml2docs script</p>
</resolution>
</defect>

<defect status="open" originator="Mark">
<title>Improve the tables implementation</title>
<p>The HTML version of this is extremely sparse at present; the LaTeX
DC does better.</p>
</defect>

<defect status="closed" originator="Mark" date="15-Sep-1999">
<title>LaTeX: global declarations</title>
<p>A collection of \newcommands at the head of the document.</p>
<p>Mmm, I've now forgotten what this means.  I can't remember if we
discussed this and decided it was probably a bad idea.  There's
support for something like this in the data content attributes for the
latexgraphics notation (see notations.text), but this might be too
arcane for the future, and in any case isn't implemented (not least
because it's arcane).</p>
<p>Quoth Mark:</p>
<p>if the mathematics in a document relies
on user-defined macros then you have to define them in each math element,
since there is no persistence of LaTeX definitions between math elements
in the SGML (is there?)</p>
<p>Discussed in email to norman of 15 Sep 1999</p>
<p>Ah yes..., I remember</p>
<resolution status="fixed" author="Norman" date="5-Jun-2000"
	note="starlink-0.7.dtd, rev 1.3; programcode-0.7.dtd, rev 1.12">
<p>Added mdefs element, which sits between paragraphs.</p>
</resolution>
</defect>

<defect status="closed" originator="Mark" date="15-Sep-1999">
<title>LaTeX: programcode formatting</title>
<p>The results are very ugly at present.</p>
<resolution status="fixed" author="Norman" date="15-May-2000">
<p>Use an adapted version of the SST macros in the generated LaTeX.
Not really worth worrying about too much, as there might well be a substantial
redesign of the output in future.</p>
</resolution>
</defect>

<defect status="closed" originator="Mark">
<title>HTML: programcode formatting</title>
<p>This is still pretty hideous.  Should be made to look more like the
current star2html output.</p>
<resolution status="fixed" author="Norman" date="29-May-2000">
<p>Looks much like star2html output.  This conformance hasn't been
extensively tested, and the formatting of the authorlist, at least, is
significantly different, but there's not much point in getting every
last feature correct, since this should be resolved in the upcoming
redesign of both the formatters and the format.</p>
</resolution>
</defect>

<defect status="open" originator="Norman" date="29-May-2000">
<title>HTML: programcode next/previous and TOC occasionally wrong</title>
<p>At great effort, the HTML formatting of programcode documents now
both splits routines into separate files (not toooo hard) and manages
`up' links to the rest of the document (damn hard, as it turns out).
I think there are still a few wrinkles in the way that
next/previous/up links work.</p>
<resolution status="deferred" author="Norman" date="29-May-2000">
<p>I don't plan to fix this.  Because of the way the programcode
down-converter is structured, most of the business of linking up and
down to the programcode documents is vaguely nightmarish, since it's
difficult to use the same mechanism
that the rest of the down-converter uses.  This sort of problem is one
of the big reasons supporting a redesign of the down-converters, so
that they work via an intermediate XML file, so that the messy
business of fixing up cross-references can be done more sanely.</p>
</resolution>
</defect>

<defect status="open" originator="Mark" date='29-May-2000'>
<title>LaTeX: underscore and angle-brackets wrongly formatted</title>
<p>Underscore appears in generated LaTeX as \char95, which comes out
funny.  Left and right angle brackets appear unescaped, so come out
like upside-down punctuation.</p>
</defect>

<defect status="open" originator="Mark" date='6-Jun-2000'>
<title>HTML: Generated maths bitmaps wrongly positioned</title>
<p>Bitmaps could do with some sort of strut, so that, for example, a
single minus sign doesn't drop to the bottom of the line.</p>
<p>This is actually a consequence of the way dvi2bitmap forms its
images, and the fact that DVI files contain no notion of baselines --
they're just collections of characters at random points on the page.
That means it's probably not that easy to fix.</p>
<p>This has actually been fixed to some extent, since dvi2bitmap now
has a strut special, which the img-eqlist.pl script uses to create the
`correct' amount of space round maths.  It's still not properly fixed,
however, since there's a tricky unresolved issue about what alignment
the generated HTML &lt;img&gt; tag should give the maths image.  This
alignment, and the size of the generated bitmap, interact messily.</p>
</defect>

<defect status="closed" originator="Norman/Mark" date='12-Jun-2000'>
<title>HTML: Spacing of \scriptstyle maths is wrong</title>
<p>Spacing in \scriptstyle in generated maths bitmaps is wrong.  If you write
$x^{123}$ or ${\scriptstyle \cos x}$, the `123' and the `cos' are
strung out from each other.</p>
<resolution status="noproblem" author="Norman" date="12-Jun-2000">
<p>This is actually a dvi2bitmap defect, and it'll be resolved when
it's resolved there.</p>
</resolution>
</defect>

</defectgroup>

<defectgroup>
<title>General</title>

<defect status="open" originator="Mark" date="16-Aug-1999">
<title>Does the Makefile work on all platforms? </title>
<p>I haven't checked this (and the Tru64 make is so crappy that
the answer is almost certainly `no'), but the point is moot at
the moment, as Jade builds only on the Linux boxes.</p>
<resolution status="deferred" author="Norman" date="00-Jan-2000">
<p>By the time this becomes live, we might be running Linux on the
alphas, too!</p>
</resolution>
</defect>

<defect status="open" originator="Mark" date="15-Sep-1999">
<title>Document templates </title>
<p>`Some hints and tips, in the form of examples, might be useful
(for instance creative use of entities)'.  Norman doubts very much that
we ought to be encouraging `creative' use of entities....</p>
</defect>


</defectgroup>
</defectslist>
