<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE defectslist SYSTEM "defects.dtd">

<defectslist>

<title>ESP issues list</title>
<version>$Revision$</version>
<date>$Date$</date>

<p>This list contains the current defects list for the ESP
application.  As well as specific deficiencies, these `defects'
include items which are merely suggestions or TODOs.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, I have very little ESP time allocated this year.</p>

<p>If it's not in here, I don't plan to do anything about it.  That
probably means it's slipped through the (unfortunately rather ragged)
net, and you should remind me about it.</p>

<p>These are in chronological order, and some have a higher priority
than others.</p>

<!-- DO NOT CHANGE THE ORDER OF ELEMENTS IN THIS FILE.
     They're numbered when they're formatted, and it'd be nice to keep
     those numbers correct.
     -->

<defectgroup>
<title>Functionality</title>

<defect status="open"
	originator="Jonathan Smoker"
	originatoremail="J.Smoker@Queens-Belfast.AC.uk">
<title>ARDFIL parameter does not behave properly</title>
<p>Looking at ards.f it appears that
ESP_ARD_DRIVER returns a warning whether you type !
(=PAR__NULL, cf SUN/114) in response to the ARDFIL prompt, or
!! (=PAR__ABORT).  The latter should cause the application to
stop, and it doesn't.</p>

<p>Also, ards.f calls par_cancl, which (I think) carefully discards any value
of ardfil the user sets on the command line.  Is there some
twisted reason why this is a Good Idea?  I don't think so -- Malcolm
Currie also reported this as a problem.</p>

<p>Quoth Malcolm:
<blockquote><p>There are problems using ARD files.  First the reference documentation
for the ARDFIL parameters oit to mention that you need the ^ prefix.
The data type is _CHAR, when in fact it is GROUP.  In KAPPA/ARDMASK I only
accept a filename hence the type is FILENAME.  I accept that it is
mentioned once in the main text and in the odd example, but it wasn't
in the specification for the task I was looking at.  Thus I saw errors
like this.

<verbatim>
   ARDFIL - Masking ARD file /@gb160151_db_dk_fl.ard/ > 
   !! SUBPAR: Error finding component 'ard' in gb160151_db_dk_fl.ard
   !  SUBPAR: Failed to open HDS object associated with parameter ARDFIL
   ARDFIL - Masking ARD file /@gb160151_db_dk_fl.ard/ > gb160151_db_dk_fl.ard
   WARNING! - ARD file not used.
</verbatim>
Please could the final error message be expanded, perhaps suggesting that
there should be a ^ before the filename. 
</p></blockquote>
</p>
<p>Also, the types associated with the ARDFIL parameter seem confused.</p>
</defect>

<defect status="open"
	originator="Malcolm Currie"
	originatoremail="mjc@jach.hawaii.edu">
<title>BACK parameter misbehaving?</title>
<p>Malcolm:
<blockquote>
<p>ELLPRO generates different results depending on the BACK value. There
was some light leak on the CCD, so I ran HISTPEAK excluding the lower
left.  I ran ELLPRO with parameter BACK set to 1923.  Later I used
KAPPA/SURFIT to remove the sky variation, flat to about 1 count.  I
ran ELLPRO again but with BACK set to 0.  I saw different results,
both the radii and ther limiting radius.  So I added a constant 1923
to the sky-subtracted image and ran ELLPRO once again with BACK=1923.
The results were different from the BACK=0 case.
</p></blockquote></p>
</defect>

<defect status="open" originator="Emanuela Pompei"
originatoremail="epompei@brera.mi.astro.it" date="28-Jun-2000">
<title>GRAPHS: Mysterious end-of-file</title>
<p>GRAPHS running on an ELLFOU output file claims to find a spurious
end-of-file.</p>
</defect>

</defectgroup>


<defectgroup>
<title>Appearance and output</title>

<defect status="open"
	originator="Malcolm Currie"
	originatoremail="mjc@jach.hawaii.edu">
<title>Write computed values to parameters</title>
<p>It would be convenient if ESP/GAUFIT wrote computed
values to parameters, rather than just to a text file.</p>
</defect>

<defect status="open"
	originator="Malcolm Currie"
	originatoremail="mjc@jach.hawaii.edu">
<title>ELLPRO output and its origin</title>
<p>Malcolm:
<blockquote>
<p>The co-ordinate information output by ELLPRO ignores the origin.  The
pixel co-ordinates are with respect to the grid.  Also the unfortunately
named parameter ORIGIN (I'd prefer CENTRE) also fails to allow for
the NDF origin.
</p></blockquote></p>
</defect>

<defect status="open"
	originator="Athanassios Katsiyannis"
	originatoremail="Star@Queens-Belfast.AC.UK">
<title>ELLPRO/FOU's SIGMA parameter</title>
<p>Thanassis:
<blockquote>
<p>In ellpro and ellfou there is a parameter called SIGMA which is described
as "Standard deviation of the background". But those are two different
things (although their values are quite close so it doesn't really
matters). Could you please clarify that?</p>
</blockquote>
</p>
</defect>

<defect status="open"
	originator="Athanassios Katsiyannis"
	originatoremail="Star@Queens-Belfast.AC.UK">
<title>LOBACK: extra statistics output</title>
<p>Thanassis:
<blockquote>
<p>The loback command gives useful statistics of certain image areas.
Could you please put an extra output line at the end giving statistics
from all the samples? (for example the standard deviation, sigma, average
etc of all the individual samples).
</p>
</blockquote>
</p>
</defect>

</defectgroup>

</defectslist>
