<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE defectslist
	PUBLIC "+//IDN astro.gla.ac.uk::norman//DTD Defects List//EN"
	"defects.dtd">

<defectslist>

<title>ECHOMOP defects/issues list</title>

<version>$Revision$</version>
<date>$Date$</date>

<p>This list contains the current list of defects and issues for
ECHOMOP.  As well as specific deficiencies, these `defects' include
items which are merely suggestions or TODOs.</p>

<p>These are in no particular order, and some have a higher priority
than others.</p>

<!-- DO NOT CHANGE THE ORDER OF ELEMENTS IN THIS FILE.
     They're numbered when they're formatted, and it'd be nice to keep
     those numbers correct.
     -->

<defectgroup>
<title>Functionality</title>

<defect status="closed" originator="Ignacio Negueruela"
originatoremail="ignacio@tocai.sdc.asi.it" date="4-May-1999">
<title>Ripple on the continuum</title>
<p>Ripple superimposed on the continuum, possibly due to missing
counts?</p>
<appendices>
<email id="negueruela1" src="negueruela1.mail"/>
</appendices>
<resolution status="deferred" author="Norman" date="10-May-1999">
<p>An expert I consulted suggested:
<blockquote>
<p>Hmm. A lot depends on how bright the object is. For bright objects where
sky background is not a problem, I normally try to take the dekker limits
well into the inter-order gap. This is wider than the limits that are
normally set automatically by option 4.1. This ensures that there is
sufficient background. Is he substracting sky with option 6, or fitting
scattered light with option 22?</p>

<p>It is hard to judge whether or not this is the problem, as he doesn't
mention the amplitude of the ripple. Last year, when I was dealing with
obscenely high S:N ratios, I found that the interpolation routine for
tdetermining the spatial profile shape for optimal extraction was giving a
ripple with an amplitude about 0.003 of the signal. The cure was to ditch
optimal extraction and do simple extraction over the same limits.
</p>
</blockquote>
</p>

<p>In a later message, Ignacio reported:
<blockquote>
<p>The two problems I had seem to be in part due to the fact that
the data were taken with a fibre-fed spectrograph (though they also affect
the UES data). The difficulties can be interpreted as follows:
<ol>
<li><p>"One issue is with the use of flat  fields. With fibre data it doesnt
usually work very well if you use flat fields in the reduction as you
would with conventional echelle data. I think it is better to extract the
object spectrum and flat field spectrum individually and then divide the
object by the flat field."</p>

<p>Well, I've tried this ans it sort of works with the fibre-fed data. I am
not very happy with the results for the UES data. Neither the traditional
approach nor this other one seems to work. One possible explanation could
be that the extent of the flat orders is limited by the dekker while the
star orders are much smaller and their geometries do not much exactly. I
am not sure. I keep looking into it.</p></li>

<li><p>"The other difficulty with fibre data is that the object profile limits
need to be set very carefully else pixellation introduces noise. This is
probably what was responsible for the ripple pattern you found." </p>

<p>This seems to work correctly if you are careful defining the extent of
the object. The pixellation (ripple) effect disappears.</p>
</li>
</ol>
</p>
</blockquote>
</p>
</resolution>
</defect>

<defect status="open" originator="Orlon Petterson"
originatoremail="physokp@cantua.canterbury.ac.nz" date="4-Aug-2000">
<title>Rounding of pixel numbers</title>

<p>ECHOMOP 3.3-4: optimal extraction, as opposed to profile
extraction, seems to round pixel numbers much more often than seems
plausible.</p>
<appendices>
<email id="petterson0" src="petterson0.mail"/>
</appendices>
</defect>

<defect status="open" originator="James Bleach"
originatoremail="jnb@astro.keele.ac.uk" date="9-Aug-2000">
<title>`Hedgehog' problem</title>

<p>Quoth James:
<blockquote>
<p>I have attached two ps files to illustrate the problem that I and a
colleague of mine have encountered during the reduction of sets of WHT
echelle spectroscopy, dubbed the `hedgehog' problem. The problem is clear
in the first image and is also present on a smaller scale in the lower
spectrum of the second image, seen as small regular jumps. We found that
this problem is removed if the dekker extent is reduced (see the upper two
spectra in the second image, the only difference between these spectra is
the background definition and as a result the S/N). I am not clear on what
is causing the problem and therefore why it is solved by decreasing he
dekker extent.</p>
</blockquote>
</p>
<appendices>
<fig id="bleach1" src="bleach1.gif"/>
<fig id="bleach2" src="bleach2.gif"/>
</appendices>
</defect>

<defect status="open" originator="Rachel North"
originatoremail="rcn@astro.soton.ac.uk"
date="12-May-2000">
<title>AI option crashes!</title>
<p>Rachel North managed to produce crashes using the AI toption of
ech_idwave and saving scrunched object orders (option 14:
RESULT_TYPE: SCROBJ).</p>
</defect>

</defectgroup>

<defectgroup>

<title>Interface problems</title>

<defect status="closed"
        originator="Michael Albrow"
        originatoremail="phys170@cantua.canterbury.ac.nz"
        date="1-Feb-1999">
<title>ech_dekker and ech_object apparently yoked together</title>
<p>Michael Albrow:
<blockquote>
<p>When using
echmenu, options "4.1" and "4.2" (these are the tasks ech_dekker and
ech_object)
don't seem to be able to be invoked separately anymore. Instead, trying
either option seems to do the same as option "4" (ech_spatial).</p>
</blockquote>
</p>
<appendices>
<email id="albrow1" src="albrow1.mail"/>
</appendices>
<resolution status="fixed" author="Norman" date="16-Jul-2002">
<p>There was a bug in the option-parsing code, which in fact caused
the same problem with all suboptions.  Made <em>much</em> more robust
in release 3.3-6.</p>
</resolution>
</defect>

<defect status="closed"
         originator="Dave James"
        originatoremail="djj@st-andrews.ac.uk"
        date="14-Sep-1999">
<title>Option 4.2</title>
<p>Option 4.2 isn't `sticky'.</p>
<appendices>
<email id="djj1" src="djj1.mail"/>
</appendices>
<resolution status="fixed" author="Norman" date="26-Jul-2002">
<p>Same fix as the previous problem.</p>
</resolution>
</defect>

<defect status="open" originator="Rachel North"
originatoremail="rcn@astro.soton.ac.uk" date="12-May-2000">
<title>ech_idwave, XP and IM</title>
<p>Basically, I can't seem to export(XP) or import(IM) the arc orders from 
ech_idwave (option 10) so that the arc can be identified using the FIGARO 
command ECHARC. This is the error message I'm getting:

<verbatim>
%echarc
>echarc >IMAGE - (IMage) Collapsed echelle arc image to be fitted
>/@ECH_ARC/ >ECH_ECHAR 
>ARCTYPE - (ARctype) Type of arc /'thar'/ >
>UNINITIALISED 
>.Y.LABEL above not order number
</verbatim>
</p>

<p>Also, the single order toggle (option 24) doesn't seem to have any effect.
In addition, when I tried to use the AI option of ech_idwave, the program 
crashed...</p>

<p>Finally, when I try and save the scrunched object orders (option 14: 
RESULT_TYPE: SCROBJ) the program crashes out with this message:
<verbatim>
>*** TERMINATING  /star/bin/echomop/echmenu
>*** Received signal 11 SIGSEGV
>Segmentation fault
</verbatim></p>
</defect>
</defectgroup>

<defectgroup>
<title>Other problems</title>
<defect
    status="open"
    originator="Martin Bly"
    originatoremail="starlink@jiscmail.ac.uk"
    date="11-Nov-2002">
<title>Hyperlinking into sun152 fails</title>
<p>Although the links within the SUN/152 document still work, for some 
reason links <em>into</em> it from other Starlink documents break.
It's not clear when this started happening, since both SUN/152 and the 
HTX (hypertext linking) system have been stable for a long while.</p>
<p>Does not affect the users of the SUN/152 document itself, only the
software librarian building the complete document set, and it is on
this ground that ECHOMOP 3.3-6 will not appear on the Autumn 2002 CD.</p>
</defect>
</defectgroup>

</defectslist>

